<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Godly meditacions verye necessarie to bee sayde of all Christen men</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1546</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 124:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Godly meditacions verye necessarie to bee sayde of all Christen men</title>
                  <author>Ledley, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E. Whitchurch?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1546?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Leaf E5v: By me John Ledley.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Prayers.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:1"/>
            <p>Godly me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditacions verye neceſſarie to bee ſayde of all Chriſten men.</p>
            <p>☞ Watche and praye leſte ye fall into temptation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:2"/>
            <head type="rubric">Before thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forgeue, yf thou haſte any thing againſt any man, and remembre that thou comeſte not to God with a double hearte but lifte vp thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des without wrath or doubtynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie and moſt mercyful father, I thy poore creature and work of thy handes, do knowledge &amp; confeſſe vnto thee my manifolde ſynnes and wyckednes,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:3"/>which I from my youth vp vnto thys tyme haue greuouſly committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee in thoughte, worde, and dede, and am nowe hartely ſory for the ſame, deſiring the for the death and bloudſheding of Ieſus Chriſte to haue mercy vpon me and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue me al thoſe mine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences accordynge to thy greate mercye &amp; promiſe, which thou haſt made to
<pb facs="tcp:4443:3"/>me and al men, in Chriſt Ieſus oure Lord.</p>
            <p>O lord I knowledge &amp; confeſſe vnto thee, that in my fleſh dweleth no good thing, and that of my ſelf I am not able to do that thou requireſt of mee to be doe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore O lord I call vnto the for grace alwayes to preuente my will to al goodneſſe, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſpirit in the ſame ſtrength and hable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:4"/>to perform it: O lord make me poore in ſpirit, vile &amp; low in mine owne ſight, that I lifte not vp my hearte aboue my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but that I maye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme my ſelfe to be as a ſeruaunt to al men for to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good: O lord geue mee grace, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I be ouertaken with any kind of ſynne &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, either in thought woord or dede: or that I
<pb facs="tcp:4443:4"/>feele mine owne infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or weaknes, I maye immediatlye with hartye repentaunce retourne to the againe. Oh lord take from mee all pryde and vaine glory all hautenes of mind and preſumpcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all ſelfe loue, and ſelfe truſt, that I ſtand not to hyghe in mine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceypt: but that I may be willing to learn of euery man, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to teache.
<pb facs="tcp:4443:5"/>O lord take fro me that wicked ſpirite of ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; enui: al raſh indgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes euill ielouſye and vayne ſurmiſings, murmuring &amp; grudging, whiſpering, or backbyti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>O lord take from me al wrath: malice, and haſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, al reſpect of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the faythe, &amp; all lying, euil wordes, contencion, all flatteryng, diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, ſuperſticion, Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:5"/>&amp; ypocriſie, al lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ydle wordes &amp; all vnſtableneſſe of hert.</p>
            <p>O lrod kepe me from al erronioꝰ doctryne, &amp; falſe interpretacions of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. O lord take fro me al vnbelefe, blindneſſe of minde, hardneſſe of hart, contempt of thy woorde and commaundemente:</p>
            <p>Oh clenſe my heart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all filthineſſe, both of the fleſhe and the ſpirite, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4443:6"/>all vncleane thoughtes, and vnlawfull deſyres, euyll concupiſcence and luſt of the body O good lorde. Take fro mee alſo couetouſneſſe, all deceipt and gile in my vocation, all idelnes and ſlouthe, &amp; geue mee not ouer vnto an vnſhamefaſt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate minde: Oh lorde make mee worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre impriſonment, loſſe of goodes, wife, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yea, &amp; myne owne life for thy
<pb facs="tcp:4443:6"/>word &amp; names ſake, &amp; to reioice in it, &amp; glorifie the for it. O lord make me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to beare al occaſions with pacience, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be offered or ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen mee, &amp; not to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euil for euill, neither to ſwel nor to murmure, nor to be ſolemne, nor angry. O good lorde make me very loth and ſlow to geue occaſions of euil to any man, &amp; if I chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to
<pb facs="tcp:4443:7"/>geue any, make mee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to knowledg &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my faultes, and to amend it: good lord grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me grace that I may bee willing and free to geue, loth to take and receyue, becauſe it is more bleſſed to geue then to receaue.</p>
            <p>Oh lord graunt that I neuer enui ani good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s loue, or womens, becauſe they eyther do loue god &amp; his people, more then I
<pb facs="tcp:4443:7"/>or els that they bee belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of any more then I.</p>
            <p>O lord make me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s giftes and not to enuye them, beecauſe they bee better then mine, but rather to geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to god with my hearte deſirynge that they maye bee increaſed in them and in me.</p>
            <p>Oh lorde take fro me a careful heart in al world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thinges. And graunte
<pb facs="tcp:4443:8"/>that neyther pouertie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me neither richeſſe lift me vp, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perytie I may geue thee thankes and in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be pacient.</p>
            <p>O lord make me merie in thee without lyghtnes ſad without miſtruſt, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber without dulnes, true without deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge in thee withoute preſumptyon.</p>
            <p>Oh lord geue me humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:4443:8"/>&amp; a lowli mind, ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citie, mekenes, gentilnes, goodnes, faythefulnes, and truthe.</p>
            <p>O geue mee alſo tender mercy, louyngkindenes longſuffering and paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to beare all thinges wel that thou ſhalt ſuffer to be laide vpon me.</p>
            <p>Oh lord encreaſe my faith in the &amp; in my redemer.</p>
            <p>Oh lorde encreaſe and make perfecte my hope in thy promyſe, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:4443:9"/>my ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>Oh lorde encreaſe my loue in the and in my iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyer. O lord encreaſe in me a true and vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue to the, and to all vertue and godlineſſe, &amp; to al the elect and choſen people, whereſoeuer they be diſperſed in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world</p>
            <p>Oh lord encreaſe in me ſtrength and victorye, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all temptacions, &amp; aſſaultes of the fleſh, the
<pb facs="tcp:4443:9"/>world and the deuil, that I be not caried away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the errour of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Oh lord, geue me grace to kepe a good conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, geue me a pure hearte, a- pure mynd, and a ryghte ſpirite renew within me.</p>
            <p>Oh lorde geue me true repentaunce, and thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, and the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the holye word, and that my whole felicitie maye bee in the
<pb facs="tcp:4443:10"/>ſame word, in hearing, in readinge, in talkynge in watchinge, prainge, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, in mortifying, and ſubduing mine owne wil and membres.</p>
            <p>Oh lorde geue mee the true iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſpirites, that I be neyther decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by loue nor by hate.</p>
            <p>Oh gracious lord geue me a ſtedfaſt and perfect remembraunce of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly word, that I maye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb facs="tcp:4443:10"/>my ſelfe in it daye and nyghte.</p>
            <p>O lorde haue mercy on my wife &amp; children which thou haſt geuen me, and increaſe thy feare in oure heartes, that we may tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly loue the, and one of vs an other in thee: ſo that we maie be pure in ſoule &amp; body, and to bringe vp our children in vertue &amp; informacion of the lord. O merciful god geue me
<pb facs="tcp:4443:11"/>ſoberneſſe, pacyence, and chaſtitie. Oh lorde plant and ſowe in my heart all vertues that bee neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and required in a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, namely wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, diſcretyon tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, ſtrength, &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and geue me grace ſo to vſe them and all other giftes, whiche I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued at thy mercyfull hand, as may be moſt to thy glory and profit, and
<pb facs="tcp:4443:11"/>to my conſolacion &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort and to the prayſe of my brethren. For I dooe not require theſe peticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Oh lord of thee, tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting in mine owne right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, no but onli in thy great mercies: Oh lorde heare me. Oh forgeue me lord: Oh lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider me tarye not ouer longe, but for thyne owne ſake do it Oh my god for the citie and people which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:4443:12"/>after thy name.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ Geue al prayſe to god who alone is worthy-</head>
            <div type="rubric">
               <p>¶ Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that ye pray for the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; the quenes maieſties grace the counſel, &amp; al that be in aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or office, the congregacion of God diſperſed througheoute all the woorlde,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R.L.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer_proper">
               <p>MOſt bleſſed lorde Ieſu graunt me thy grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with me &amp; work with me: and perſeuer with me vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, &amp; that I may euer deſyre &amp; will that is
<pb facs="tcp:4443:12"/>moſt pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the, thy wil be my will, &amp; my will alway to folow thy wil, &amp; beſt agre therwith, be there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in me one will, &amp; one deſyre with thee, and that I haue no power to wil, or not to wil, but as thou wilt, or wilt not: &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me that I may die to all thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in thy world and for the: to loue to be diſpyſed, &amp; to be as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4443:13"/>vnknowne in this world graunt me alſo aboue al that can bee deſyred, that I maye reſte me in thee, and fulli in thee to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my hart for thou lord art the veri true peace of heart, and the perfect reſt bothe of body and ſoule: &amp; without the al thinges be greuous &amp; vnquyete: Wherefore in that peace that is in the one hyghe, one bleſſed, and one end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4443:13"/>goodnes ſhall I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſt me. So be it: good lord let it bee ſo.</p>
               <p>O Lord God for thy great mercye ſake, graunte me all theſe my peticions, and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mee that I may aſke them in ſuch ſorte as thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to the honor, glory, &amp; prayſe of thy holy name, to the profit of thy word and people and to my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort through
<pb facs="tcp:4443:14"/>Ieſus Chryſt, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be al honour &amp; glory world without ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <p>O Lorde thou greate and terrible God, thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kepeſt couenaunt and mercye with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue the, and do thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, let thine eares mark, and let thine eies be opened that thou mayſt heare the prayers of thy ſeruaunt which I make before thee at thys
<pb facs="tcp:4443:14"/>time, &amp; haue mercy vpon mee thy poore creature &amp; work of thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, for I haue ſinned &amp; done wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, and haue offended thy maieſtie greuouſlye, in that I haue gon back and departed from al thy precepts and iugmentes &amp; haue not folowed thy ſeruauntes the prophets that ſpake vnto mee in in thy name, but haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daye to daye prouoked
<pb facs="tcp:4443:15"/>thy iuſt wrath &amp; indigna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon agaynſte me.</p>
            <p>O Lord I knowledge &amp; confeſſe my manifolde ſynnes and wickednes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which I haue vnryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly committed againſt the in thought word and deede, fro my youthe vp, vntyll thys daye, for the whiche I am hertely ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and do vnfaynedly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, purpoſyng euer more throughe the aſſiſtaunce
<pb facs="tcp:4443:15"/>of thy grace, to walke in a newe lyfe.</p>
            <p>O lorde remembre not the numbre of my miſe-dedes, but according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy greate mercyes, thinke vpon me O lorde for thy goodnes.</p>
            <p>O Lorde for Chryſtes ſake cal to remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thy louingkindneſſe and thy tender merci y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hath been euer of olde.</p>
            <p>O lorde hide not thou
<pb facs="tcp:4443:16"/>thy face fro me, nor caſte not of thy ſeruaunte in thy diſpleaſure, for I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe my ſynnes vnto the, and hyde not myne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghteouſnes.</p>
            <p>O lord for thy mercies ſake, delyuer me from al my ſinnes and make me not a ſcorne vnto the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe.</p>
            <p>O Lorde turne not thou thy mercye fro mee, but let thy louyngkynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:16"/>&amp; truth alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue mee. O lorde helpe mee for thy name ſake, &amp; deliuer me in thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. O lord for Chriſtes ſake heare my praier, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyder the woordes of my mouth, for my miſdedes preuayle agaynſte mee. O be thou mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſynnes.</p>
            <p>O lord let the ſorowful ſyghyng of thy pryſoner come beefore thee, and
<pb facs="tcp:4443:17"/>accordinge to the power of thyne arme preſerue thoſe that bee appoynted to dye.</p>
            <p>O Lorde comforte the ſoule of thy ſeruaunt, for vnto thee dooe I lyft vp my ſoule.</p>
            <p>O lorde teache mee to numbre my dayes: that I maye applye my heart vnto wyſoome.</p>
            <p>O lord ſatiſfy me with thy merci, &amp; that ſoone, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4443:17"/>ſhall I reioyce &amp; be glad all the dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            <p>O lord loke not extrem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li what is done amiſſe in me, for I haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and before thee, &amp; am no more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be called thy ſonne yet Lorde of thy greate goodnes powre doowne ſome of thy cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes that fall from thy childrenes table, &amp; make me as one of the leaſt of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:18"/>
            <p>O lord rewarde me not accordinge to my deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, for then I muſte nedes periſh, for vnto me perteineth nothing but o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen ſhame, confuſyon, and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacion: but with thee there is mercye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes and ſaluacyon.</p>
            <p>O lorde therefore do I come vnto thee, not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in myne owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes but truſtynge onely in thy greate mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb facs="tcp:4443:18"/>and promiſes, made vnto me in Chriſte Ieſu my Lord, for whoſe ſake I beeſeche thee to clenſe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all my ſinnes, &amp; do away al mine iniquities.</p>
            <p>O lorde for thy tender mercye ſake laye not my ſynnes to my charge, but geue me grace to amend my lyfe, and walke in a pure conuerſacion, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from ſynne, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to vertue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye
<pb facs="tcp:4443:19"/>therby walke in a perfect heart, a cleane conſcience, and ſingle eye before the, this day and euermore.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight</note>
            </p>
            <p>O Lord remembre not mine offences nor the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of my forefathers neyther take thou veng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of my ſinnes, ſpare me good Lord, ſpare me, whom thou haſt redemed with thy moſte precyous bloud, and be not angrie with mee for euer, ſpare
<pb facs="tcp:4443:19"/>me good lord, ſpare me.</p>
            <p>O lord put me not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy preſence, but inclyne thyne eare vnto my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng. O lord ſtrengthen thy ſeruaunt, and healpe the ſon of thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</p>
            <p>O lorde repleniſhe my heart with grace wiſdom and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>O Lorde embrace my ſoule with thy promiſes, and let thy mercies couer myne infyrmities.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:20"/>
            <p>O Lorde for Chriſtes deathe and bloude ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, conſider mine infir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mityes which are manie, and helpe &amp; beare myne imperfectyon, and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me from al kindes of euylles, that I dooe not obey vnto them: as from adulterye, fornicacyon, vncleanneſſe, wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, ydolatrie, good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer me. From witche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, lying, hatred, vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:20"/>zeale, wrath, ſtrife, ſedicion good lorde deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me. From ſectes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying, whiſpering, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytyng, bryngyng vp of euyll thynges, good lord delyuer me. From mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, dronkennes, gloutto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, and from that ſpirite of euil ielouſy, good lord delyuer mee. From en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyinge of other whyche loue thee and thy people more then I, or bee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
<pb facs="tcp:4443:21"/>of the or of thy pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople more then I, &amp; from ſwellyng at other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes giftes, good lord deliuer me. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurmiſing, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, lowring, grudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng, muttri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> words be not ſpoked to my mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, good Lord for thy great mercies ſake deliuer me, that I do at no tyme en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie any good manne or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s loue, but labour to encreaſe it, that theyre
<pb facs="tcp:4443:21"/>proſperitie in worde, and prayſe of other maye bee my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reioiſing.</p>
            <p>O lord graunt me that I may bee lowe in myne owne ſight, to put doune my ſelfe to beare occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to wreſtle with fleſh &amp; bloud, &amp; get the victori.</p>
            <p>O lord graunt me this gift, that I may be ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeake &amp; ſlowe to wrathe, that my hearte do not go after no
<pb facs="tcp:4443:22"/>wicked and euill imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions. O lord geue me grace to walke ſo, that I geue none euil occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to auoyde all ſuſpicious thinges, wherby euill oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions maye growe.</p>
            <p>O lord aſſiſt me with thy ſpirite, that I maye la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure to mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne peace to increaſe loue &amp; to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue.</p>
            <p>O merciful father, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that I maye proſper in
<pb facs="tcp:4443:22"/>all vertue, in longe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, gentilnes, goodnes, faithefulnes, mekeneſſe, temperaunce, ſtrength, &amp; pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with al ſuch like vertues as ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded me to walke in thy holye law. O lord geue me ioie in thy holy ghoſt, that I may reioyce in thy holye ſcriptures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al my whole pleaſure, ioye, felycitye, and conſolacyon, may be
<pb facs="tcp:4443:23"/>in thy holy word night &amp; day, in reading, muſyng, &amp; talking of the ſame to thy glory, &amp; my edifying. O lord aſſiſt thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt this world, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne pompe, pleaſure and beutie therof, that it may be vnto me as vyle duſt, ſlime filthines, and aſſhes, that I maie haue this world as though I had it not, &amp; that it maye ſerue mee, &amp; I not it, that
<pb facs="tcp:4443:23"/>I maye take my parte therof with thankesge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng vnto my neceſſitie, that I do not vſe thy cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures voluptuouſli, but that I maye at all times lyue ryghteouſly, ſoberly and godly in thys lyfe.</p>
            <p>O lord geue me grace, to walke with a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience bothe beefore thee and towardes al men, in bying and ſellyng and in all other my doynges to
<pb facs="tcp:4443:24"/>caſt away all lying, craft and diſceit, that I be not a reader of thy holy word and a talker onelye, but that it maye appeare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in my life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacyon.</p>
            <p>O lord graunt vnto thy ſeruaunt the ſtrength of thy holy ſpirit to ſubdue thys my bodye of ſynue, with the hole luſtes ther of, that it may bee made obedyente, bothe in will, mynd,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:24"/>and members to do thy will, that it maye bee weake, vyle, ſymple, and of no reputacion in hys owne ſight, by the way of faſteng, praier, &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with a ſure faithe in thy promyſes made in thy ſonne Chryſte Ieſu my Lorde, that I maye bee lowlye hearted, humble minded, gentyl ſpyryted, and to all vertues obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyente.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:26"/>
            <p>O lorde geue me grace to bridle my mouthe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al vayne and lyght com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and geue me an vnderſtandyng heart with a diſcrete mouthe, that neither filthines nor folyſh talking, nor ieſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whiche are not comelye, procede out of my mouth but rather geuing of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. O lord my ſauiour, encreaſe my fayth to the and in thy chryſt, &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:4443:26"/>faythe to beleue thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. O lord my redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, encreaſe my loue to dooe thy will, and to thy righteous people.</p>
            <p>O lord my iuſtifyer en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe in mee a ſure hope of my ſaluacion, without doubt or waueri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, &amp; without pryde or preſumpcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſo that in aduerſitie I maye bee pacient, and geue the thankes in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:27"/>&amp; ſerue thee with reuerence &amp; godlye feare all the dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            <p>O lord encreaſe in mee all other vertues conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt and agreable to a godly lyfe, for I com vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee O Lord, as vnto the well and euerlaſtyng fountayne of all healthe and ſaluacyon.</p>
            <p>O heauenlye father lette mee and all other where ſoeuer they bee diſperſed
<pb facs="tcp:4443:27"/>througheoute the whole worlde, lyue in thy ſight, which ſeke thy holy word to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entent to forſake ſin &amp; all worldly liuing, &amp; to leade a godly conuerſaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on innocently before the.</p>
            <p>O lorde defend thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte from all errour, and falſe opinions, that I be not deceiued and ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed awaye in erroure of the wycked, but that I may growe in grace and
<pb facs="tcp:4443:28"/>knoweledge of our lorde &amp; ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O lord geue me a pure iudgement &amp; a reuerente in thy holy woord, that I maye thereby auoyde all vayne affeccions &amp; raſh iudgementes.</p>
            <p>O lorde geue me wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, knowledg &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to perceiue thoſe falſe lyinge, flatterynge ſpirites, whiche dooe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the heartes of inno
<pb facs="tcp:4443:28"/>centes, &amp; begyle vnſtable ſoules.</p>
            <p>O lord make me to bee contente with this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to be my wyfe,
<note place="margin">Let wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> ſai (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and let her loue alwaies ſatiſfie me. O lord geue her an hart of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, and ſet thy feare alwayes before her eyes, that ſhe may be obedient in word, dede &amp; thought to al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is thy wil O lord geue vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power
<pb facs="tcp:4443:29"/>of thy holy ſpirit, to rule, gouerne, and brynge vp theſe our chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in all godly feare &amp; knoweledge of thy holye worde, and that we maye be theyr ſhewtoken, in al godlines and vertue to the prayſe of thy holye name.</p>
            <p>O lorde ſaue my ſoule whether it be thorow pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſperytye or aduerſytye, loſſe or gayne, ſyckeneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4443:29"/>or health, lyfe or death.</p>
            <p>O lord, ayde, ſtrengthe, ſuccoure and defende thy ſeruaunt in all aduerſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, tribulacion, and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, and ſuffre not thy ſeruaunt to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue hys ſtrengthe.</p>
            <p>O lord encreaſe my ioie that I may reioice in per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecucyon and embrace it to my conſolacion and coumeforte, and thynke my ſeelfe happye and
<pb facs="tcp:4443:30"/>bleſſed, when I am coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthye to ſuffer ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke for thy name ſake. O lord take fro my hart the care of all worldelye thinges only ſette before my eyes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioye of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſſe, that I may ioie therin, &amp; deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame for the great reward that is laide vp in heauen for chriſtes ſake, for al thoſe that with pacience ſuffer in aduerſitie, &amp; continue
<pb facs="tcp:4443:30"/>in wel doing vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end.</p>
            <p>O lorde laye not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes charge, nor looke not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my vilenes, for I am but duſte earthe &amp; aſhes, yet Lorde I haue taken vpon mee, and am bolde to com vnto the through the merytes of Chryſtes deathe and bloude ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, to laye my prayers beefore thee, requyrynge mercy, pardon, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:31"/>of al my ſinnes, and alſo the aſſiſtaunce of thy grace to dooe thy wyll all the dayes of my lyfe, and to obtayne all theſe my peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s through Ieſus Chryſte thy deare ſonne and my onlye Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure, to whom be al honour and glory nowe and euer Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>☞ By me Iohn Ledley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:31"/>
            <head>¶ A godly prayer for all Chryſten men.</head>
            <p>O Almyghtye and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlyuyng God of all thinges, before whoſe eyes al thinges lyeth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare, haue a reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte vnto mee (O thou God of my lyfe &amp; ſhewe me the lighte of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes. Let my prayers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp before thy preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; be accepted in thy ſight for Ieſus Chryſtes ſake.
<pb facs="tcp:4443:32"/>Geue mee ſeede vnto my hearte (Oh lord &amp; buyld my vnderſtandyng that I may dwell in the feare of thy hand al the dayes of my lyfe, that I maye know the, thou only true god, &amp; Ieſus Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ſent For I com vnto the (Oh Lord) thou louer of ſoules, not hoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng in myne owne righ teouſneſſe, but truſtinge onely vppon the multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:4443:32"/>of thy great mercies whiche thou haſte layde forth before the eies of al people, offering ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the whole worlde, and haſt promiſed, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he be of the whole generacion of man, that wyll obey to thy grace, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent, and tourne vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly from theyr ſynnes that they ſhould haue fre remiſſyon and forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes throughe Ieſꝰ chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4443:33"/>oure lord whiche is oure onelye aduocate &amp; medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, in whom oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatyon lyeth, of whome thou haſt ſayde: Thys is my deare ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed &amp; wel pacyfyed. For thys thy ſonnes ſake, by whom I am bolde to come vnto thee, whyche appeareth now in thy ſight, making contynuall interceſſyon for vs, haue mercy vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4443:33"/>me (O thou mighty god) and forgeue mee all my ſynnes which I haue vn ryghteouſlye committed againſte thee in thought word, or dede. Oh let me fele thy mercies towards me, for I do confeſſe my ſinnes vnto the (Oh lord &amp; hide not myne vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>punctel</ex>
               </expan> I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg myne offences, and accuſe my ſelfe before the Lord of all my miſdedes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:34"/>helpe me O god my ſaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our for the glorye of thy name. O delyuer &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue me my ſinnes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of thy names ſake. Remember not the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my youthe, O lord but think vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy great mercyes and couenaunt, made vnto me in Chryſt Ieſu. O moſt mercyfull father, conſyder myne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, whych are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and greate, and beare
<pb facs="tcp:4443:34"/>myne imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy ſonne my ſauiour Ieſus Chryſtes ſake which had good experience of infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes, that he myght be merciful to all them that are tempted. O Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how the enemie hath gotten an open way into my fleſhe wherin I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that there dwelleth nothing but ſinne, wretch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>edneſſe and miſerie.</p>
            <p>Therefore I come vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4443:35"/>the O Lord my God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyryng thee for Chryſtes ſake to renewe in mee a right ſpirite, that I may receyue ſtrength and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes to do thy wil, and to ſtande agaynſt all the craftie aſſaultes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, that they maye haue no place in mee, but that the olde manne, which I beare aboute in my body may be crucifyed, &amp; day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye in me, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luſtes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:35"/>of ſynne may vtterly bee deſtroyed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more be renewed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of my mynd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the life of chriſt may alwaies ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare in mee. Good lorde deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all kindes of euil, as fornication, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſnes, maliciouſnes enuy, murder, debate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte: good lorde deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiſperyng, backbytynge, hatynge of thee and from euyll yelouſye,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:36"/>from doyng of wronge, pryde, boaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng vp of euyll thinges: good lord deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adultri, vaine glory, ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, wantonnes, ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, witchecraft, hatred, variaunce, zeale, wrathe, ſtryfe, ſedicion, ſectes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying dronkennes, glot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonye, and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>Good lord for thy great mercyes ſake delyuer me and graunt me grace (O
<pb facs="tcp:4443:36"/>Lorde) to haue thee all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before myne eyes, that I maye alſo haue a reſpecte vnto thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that whatſoeuer I thinke, ſaye, or do, may bee agreable to thy holye word, that I be not min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as the vngodlye or wycked men are. Let me haue no pleaſure in ſuche thynges as pleaſe them: make mee lowe in myne owne ſyghte (O Lorde)
<pb facs="tcp:4443:37"/>that the foote of pryde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertake me not. Let not the hand of the vngodly caſt me downe, but bowe my hearte alwayes vnto thee, that I maye ſerue thee without feare all the dayes of my lyfe in ſuch holynes &amp; righteouſnes, as is acceptable beefore thee. Remoue from mee vanytyes and lyes, take fro mee the luſtes of the body. Let not the deſires
<pb facs="tcp:4443:37"/>of vnclennes take holde vppon me, &amp; geue me not ouer vnto an vnſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and obſtinate mind: but hold me alwaies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy nourture and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection. Of thy fatherlye mercye leaue mee not to my ſelf, but ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by mee, for I am to weake of myne owne power to doo any thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good, but my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe &amp; ſtrength lyeth
<pb facs="tcp:4443:38"/>onelye in thee. Therefore (Oh Lorde) I come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, requyring mercye in thy ſyghte, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy grace, that I maye be ſtrengthened with myght in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward man, and be armed with thy holy armoure, which is the breſt plate of right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, the ſhyld of faith the hope of ſaluacion for an helmet, and the ſword of the ſpyryte whyche is
<pb facs="tcp:4443:38"/>thy holye woorde, that I may ſtande perfecte in al that is thy wyll, and bee founde worthy (through chriſt) to receaue a croune of lyfe, whyche thou haſt promyſed to al them that loue thee in pureneſſe of mynde. O Lorde, plante in me tru obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thy holye lawe that the cares of thys worlde choke not thy word in me. Kepe me alſo from the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:39"/>of ryches, and al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanly deſyres, that all vertues maye be planted in me. Good Lorde geue me grace to walke before thee all the dayes of this my pilgremag w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience and pure mind that whan thou ſhalt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to rewarde euerye manne according to hys dedes, I may reioice and not be made aſhamed of thee at thy commynge.
<pb facs="tcp:4443:39"/>Encreaſe my faythe O lorde my ſauioure in the, &amp; in thy Chriſt. Encreaſe my loue O my redemer to thee, and to thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people, Encreaſe a ſure hope in me of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion, O my iuſtifyer. Encreaſe ſtrength in me to ouercom ſynne, and to ſtande agaynſte all euill temptacyons, that theye haue no place in me. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in me perfect vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandyng
<pb facs="tcp:4443:40"/>and pure iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in thy word, that I be, not deceaued and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed awaye in the errour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked. But graunt (O Lorde) that I maye grow in grace, and in the knowledge of oure Lord &amp; ſauyour Ieſus Chriſt. Let thy kyngdome come vnto me, whyche is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, peace, and ioye in thy holye ghoſte, longeſufferyng, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilnes, good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:40"/>faythfulnes, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peraunce, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; pacyence, with all ſuch lyke vertues as are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto me in thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly worde, that in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous things I may geue thee thankes, and in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie be pacient, that I be not lyfted vp with the one nor oppreſſed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. O let all worldely thynges be vile vnto me for thee. Let mee not bee
<pb facs="tcp:4443:41"/>merye with the ioye that is without thee, &amp; let mee deſyre nothing beſyd the. Make me to lift my hart oftentimes to the. And if I chaunce to fall or ſlip, make me to thynk on the and be ſory with a ſtede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte purpoſe of amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, O Lorde I geue o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer my ſelfe into thy holy handes, deſyryng the for Chryſtes ſake, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye remayne vnder thy migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye
<pb facs="tcp:4443:41"/> protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſtrong defence of thy power, and that thy holi aungel may alwayes pytche his tent rounde aboute mee, and kepe me in all my waies. Good Lorde geue mee the ioyefulnes of hearte and peace of conſcyence, contynual gladnes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy word &amp; ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may euermore be thakfull vnto thee, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4443:42"/>prayſe thy name, O lord thynke vpon all thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whyche are ſtrawed here and there from the fartheſt partes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth whyche be entred into co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunt with the and ar mynded to walke after thy wil, graunt (Oh lord that we may grow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in loue thorowe the knoweledge of thy holye worde, to kepe the vnitie of the ſpririte, throughe
<pb facs="tcp:4443:42"/>the bonde of peace, to the vtter confounding of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and all falſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; to kepe vs cleane from ypocryſye and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtycion, and to make vs ſtrong in peſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We beſeche the to heare vs good Lorde.</p>
            <closer>☞ Geue prayſe to God.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:43"/>
            <p>O Lord moſt mighty and fearful god, to all them that hate thee, &amp; that folowe theyr owne wayes, &amp; ſeeke not to doe thy wyll, wee thy ſymple creatures, which laboure to do thy wil, O merciful god, do ſee by thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe iudgemente of thy woorde, thy fearſe wrath and terrible indignacion agaynſte thys realine of England, O lord, for deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſyng
<pb facs="tcp:4443:43"/>of thy preachers &amp; meſſengers, and for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnder fote thy moſt holy word, and now wee ſee thy wrath is kindled. O lorde, who ſhalbe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to quenche it, &amp; we for our partes, O lord, do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe that we be worthi of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plagues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt deuiſed agaiſt vs, o moſt mighty god, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, wee beſeche the moſte merciful father vnworthi
<pb facs="tcp:4443:44"/>to be called thy children, loke not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our deſerts, or worthynes, but vpon thy fauourable mercye, whyche thou haddeſt in the olde tyme vpon the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael, yf they repented vnto the, o lord thou diddeſt preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and kept them from cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of all other nacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; diddeſt euer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd them a faithfull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerner or ruler. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more
<pb facs="tcp:4443:44"/> moſt mercyfull father although they wer deſtroyed for theyr wick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>edneſſe, &amp; left but a ſmall people, yet neuertheleſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they tourned vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly to the, thou O lord euer gaueſt them the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye ouer all theyr ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, ſo that they might dwell as breethren togee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, peaceably in theyr- owne lande, whiche thou gaueſte them. Thou arte
<pb facs="tcp:4443:45"/>the ſame lord, &amp; thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for euer, and now O lord we that ſeke to do thy will, beyng but a ſmall people, do beſech thee of thy great mercye, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake oure onelye peace maker to turne awaye thy great wrath; and terrible indig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, which we haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued in thys realme of England, and ſhewe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion vpon vs good
<pb facs="tcp:4443:45"/>Lorde, as thou dyddeſte vpon the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell in the olde tyme, though not for our ſakes O Lorde whyche haue deſerued thy wrathe, but for thy moſte myghtye &amp; gloryous names ſake, O lord: for yf thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſte deſtroye vs, and bryng vs to deſolacyon, as we haue deſerued, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde thy moſte migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye name, and thy holye
<pb facs="tcp:4443:46"/>worde be euyll ſpoken of through vs in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world Wherfore we beſeche the moſt mercifull father, to nurture and correcte vs, not as we haue deſerued, but with thy fauourable mercye, not in thy furye, but with thy fatherly py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and deliuer vs not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of our enemies, neither take not thy holy worde from vs, O Lorde, and here wee
<pb facs="tcp:4443:46"/>confeſſe vnto the, O lord all oure wickedneſſe, the whych are more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre then the heares of our heade and they preſſe vs ſo doune, O Lorde, that oure heartes almoſt fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, &amp; we dare ſkarſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſume vnto the.</p>
            <p>Yet neuertheles, through CHRISTE whyche is our ryghteouſnes, and hath pacyfyed thy wrath we are bolde to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4443:47"/>thee, O lorde being ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for oure faultes, euen from our verye heartes, deſyri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thee for his death and paſſions ſake, which is our onely mediatoure and redemer: to forgeue vs all oure ſynnes: that euer we haue commytted eyther in thought, worde or deede, &amp; now, O lorde, wee geue ouer our ſelues into thy holy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and with all oure heartes do
<pb facs="tcp:4443:47"/>deſyre to doe whatſoeuer thou wouldeſt haue vs to do, beſeching the, O lord to aſſyſt vs with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of thy holye ſpiryte, that wee hence forth may liue accordynge to thy moſte godly and bleſſed wyll, &amp; that we may labour and ſtudy to ſerue the in new<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of life, &amp; that we may willingly take vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe and folow thy ſteppes, O lorde Chryſt al the daies
<pb facs="tcp:4443:48"/>of our lyfe. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, O Lord, we beſech thee to geue vs grace to be thankefull in our con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſacion, and liuing, for all the greate benefites y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee haue receyued at thy hande, ſo that wee maye enioye them to thy glori, and our comforte. Fyrſt, we thanke thee, O Lord of thy great mercye and recreacion. Secondli, we thanke thee, O lord, that
<pb facs="tcp:4443:48"/>when wee were fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſtruction, throughe our conſenting to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiltie of the enemye, thou of thy great mercye dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte by Ieſus Chryſte rayſe vs vp againe. And we thanke thee, O Lord, that it hathe pleaſed thee to ſuffre thy holye worde the foode of oure ſoules, to haue free paſſage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs, and haſte ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a will to ſeke it, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4443:49"/>a defyre to beleue it. Fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore wee thanke the, O Lord for Mary oure Quene, whych thou haſt geuen vs to be our ruler &amp; gouernour vnder thee, whom thou haſte delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs by thy wyſedome through thy greate pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; myghtye arme, from the handes of all her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, we beſeche thee, O Lord, to geue her wiſdom from thy holy heauens, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4443:49"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the throne of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe may rule all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt made her gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor of, accordinge to thy moſt holy &amp; bleſſed wil, o lorde &amp; that ſhe maye la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure &amp; deſire to folowe al thinges that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in thy holy law, al the dayes of her lyfe, &amp; that ſhee maye throughe thee, O Lord, be ſtabliſhed in her kingdom, &amp; ouercom all her enemies &amp; oures,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:50"/>as theſe moſte godly and verteous women. Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra and Iudith dyd, who by theyr godly conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon with prayer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience through thee O Lord ouercame the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael in the olde tyme.</p>
            <p>And that thou wouldeſt voucheſafe, O Lorde, to geue grace and wyſdom to al them that thou haſt appoynted to haue rule
<pb facs="tcp:4443:50"/>ouer vs, that they maye obeye to thy will O lord, and exercyſe them ſelues in thy lawes bothe daye and nyghte, with feruent prayer obedyentely, and that they may deſyre too execute theyr offyce, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to thy wyll, O lord and that wee as louynge ſubiectes maye (not for feare of punyſhemente, but for conſcyence ſake) obeie to oure Quene and
<pb facs="tcp:4443:51"/>gouernour in al thinges that is agreeable to thy wyll O Lorde, and to all them that are in auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ouer vs, and wee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee, O Lorde for Chryſtes ſake, that euery one of vs, both hygh and lowe in hys degree, maye walke in oure conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, heere in Englande, as maie bee to thy glory, O Lord, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and edyfying of all
<pb facs="tcp:4443:51"/>other nacions that whereas they backebyte vs as euyll dooers, theye maye ſee oure good woorkes &amp; prayſe GOD in the day of vyſytacyon.</p>
            <p>O Lorde geue peace in oure tyme. Amen.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy on the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregacion diſperſed ouer all the yearthe.</p>
            <closer>☞ Geue God the prayſe.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:52"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer neceſſary to bee ſayde at all tymes.</head>
            <p>O Bountifull Ieſu, O ſwete Sauiour O Chryſte the ſonne of God, haue pitie vpon me mercifully heare me and deſpyſe not my prayers. Thou haſt created me of nothinge, thou haſt rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of ſynne, deathe, and hell neither with gold nor ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:52"/>but with thy mooſle precyous body once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vppon the croſſe, and thyne owne bloud ſhede once for all for my raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, therefore caſte mee not away, whom thou by thy greate wyſdome haſt made, deſpiſe me not who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſte redemed with ſuch a precious treaſure. Nor lette my wyckednes deſtroye that, whyche thy goodnes hathe buylded.
<pb facs="tcp:4443:53"/>Nowe whyles I lyue, O Ieſu haue mercy on me, for yf I dye oute of thy fauoure, it wyl be to late afterward to call for thy mercye, whyles I haue tyme to repente, looke vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon mee with thy mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eies, as thou diddeſt voucheſafe to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Peter thine Apoſtle, that I maye bewaile my ſynfull lyfe and obtayne thy fauour, and dye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.
<pb facs="tcp:4443:53"/>I reknowledge the yf thou ſhouldeſt deale with mee accordynge to verye iuſtyce, I haue deſerued euerlaſtynge deeathe.</p>
            <p>Therefore I appeale to thy hyghe throne of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, truſtynge to obtayne Goddes fauoure, not for my merytes, but for thy merites, o Ieſu, who haſt geuen thy ſelfe an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſacrifyce to thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to peaſe hys wrathe,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:54"/>and to bryng all ſynners trulye repentynge and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendynge theyr euyl life into his fauour agayne. Accept mee O Lorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhalbee ſaued, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue my ſynnes, geue me grace to leade a godlye &amp; innocent lyfe, graunt me thy heauenlye wyſdome, enſpyre my hearte with faythe, hope, and charitye geue mee grace to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:4443:54"/>in proſperytye, pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in aduerſytye, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente to my rulers, faithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto them that truſt me dealing truly with al menne, to lyue chaſtelye in wedlocke, to abhorre adultry, fornicacion, and al vncleanes, to do good after my power vnto all menne, to hurte no man that thy name maye bee gloryfyed in me, duryng thys preſente lyfe, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:4443:55"/>I afterwarde maye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne euerlaſtynge lyfe thorowe thy mercye and the merytes of thy paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ Another godly prayer.</head>
            <p>O Heauenlye father, God almyghty, I pray and beſech thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, beninglye to beholde mee thy vnworthye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, that I maye by gyfte of thy holy ſpyrite,
<pb facs="tcp:4443:55"/>feruently deſyre thy king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom, that I maye know thy will, and worke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Geue me (O Lord) wiſedom: Make me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, pacient, and ſtrong in thee. Kepe me lord, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſleyghtie inuaſion of the olde wily ſerpent. De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende me from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles and curſynges of euyll tongues: Lette thy mighti arme be my ſhild againſt all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malignitie
<pb facs="tcp:4443:56"/>of this wicked worlde. Remembre not (O Lord) myne offences: inſtructe, &amp; prepare me to repent, to bee ſorye for my ſynnes. Make me to loue iuſtice and hate wronge, to doo good, and abſteyne from all euels: that I may bee worthye, to bee called thy chylde. To thee bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4443:56"/>
            <head>¶ Another prayer.</head>
            <p>THe lord oure god be with vs, as he hathe benne with oure fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, and forſake vs not neyther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw hys ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from vs. But be gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto vs, and thinke vpon his couenaunt that he hath made with Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaack and Iacob his faithfull ſeruauntes: and geue vs all ſuche an hearte that we may loue
<pb facs="tcp:4443:57"/>and ſerue hym, yea: and performe hys wyll with an hole heart &amp; of a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng minde. He open our heartes, (Further &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) in hys lawes and in hys commaundementes, ſende vs hys peace, heare our prayers, be at one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, &amp; neuer forſake vs in the tyme of trouble. But to bow oure heartes vnto hym, that wee maye walke in all hys wayes
<pb facs="tcp:4443:57"/>here on earth and to kepe hys commaundementes, ordinaunces, and lawes, whiche hee commaunded our fathers, and that our heartes maye be perfecte to walke with God all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of oure lyues, this grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for thy deare ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſake Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde and onlye ſauyoure. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>¶ FINIS. ¶</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
